Register of the Louis Raemaekers Papers and Artwork
Hoover Institution Archives
- Medium Format Artwork, 1914-1945. (Box 23-40)
  - Political cartoons (Box 23)
    - Germany, 1918-1939 (Box 28)
      - Pencil and charcoal
        - French language
          - "Un second ‘Kulturkampf' ?" (Folder 28: 30)
          - "Souvent Boche varie, bien fol qui s'y fie!" (Folder 28: 31)
          - "Sur la glace internationale" (Folder 28: 32)
          - "Vienne" (Folder 28: 33)
        - German language. "Wer Gott einen Arm gibt, Dem gibt er auch den Verstand" (Folder 28: 34)
      - Watercolor
        - Dutch language. "Twee candidate" (Folder 28: 35)
        - English language. "The Berlin-Bagdad snake" (Folder 28: 36)
        - French language. "Les expulsés" (Folder 28: 37)
        - German language. "Friede sei ihr erstes Geläute" (Folder 28: 38)
    - Great Britain, 1918-1939.
      - Dutch language (Folder 29: 1-19)
      - English language
        - "Almost too good to be true!" (Folder 29: 20)
        - "Ark Royal" (Folder 29: 21)
        - "The big stick" (Folder 29: 22)
        - "The ‘Big Stick' " (different image) (Folder 29: 23)
        - "God bless you all!" (Folder 29: 24)
      - French language
        - "A Genève on a retrouvé la momie de ‘l' oncle Arthur' (Henderson)" (Folder 29: 25)
        - "Un accord entre l'Irlande et l'Angleterre?" (Folder 29: 26)
        - "Anthony Hamlet: L'être ou ne pas l'être... that is the question!" (Folder 29: 27)
        - "Le grand débat aux Communes: Comment un jeune et un ancien ministre en sortent" (Folder 29: 28)
        - "Ma décision est irrévocable: Mon frère est roi" (Folder 29: 29)
        - "Premier avril: Lloyd George écrit la ‘Vérité' sur les réparations" (Folder 29: 30)
        - "Réveil" (Folder 29: 31)
    - Italy, 1918-1939.
      - Dutch language (Folder 29: 32-36)
      - English language
        - "Be careful baby! History repeats itself!" (Folder 29: 37)
        - "Oliver asks for more" (Folder 29: 38)
      - French language
        - "L'essence" (Folder 29: 39)
        - "On n'est jamais trahi que par ses serviteurs" (Folder 29: 40)
        - "Pas de guerre pendant la saison de la pluie" (Folder 29: 41)
        - "Poker éthiopien ou mondial?" (Folder 29: 42)
        - "Rome vaut bien un parapluie" (Folder 29: 43)
        - "Rome vaut bien une messe" (Folder 29: 44)
        - "Un succès" (Folder 29: 45)
        - "Le tableau diplomatique du Comte Ciano" (Folder 29: 46)
    - Jews, 1918-1939. (Box 30)
      - Dutch language (Folder 30: 1-5)
      - French language
        - "Le Juif sera brûlé: Dédié au peuple de Lessing" (Folder 30: 6)
        - "Les Juifs-errants" (Folder 30: 7)
    - League of Nations and the problem of peace, 1918-1939., See also Europe, 1918-1939
      - Untitled and unidentified (Folder 30: 8)
      - Dutch language (Folder 30: 9-33)
      - French language
        - "A ceux qui cherchent la guerre au nom de la paix" (Folder 30: 34)
        - "Au taureau! Au taureau!" (Folder 30: 35)
        - "Aux choix" (Folder 30: 36)
        - "Ceux qui avant tout veulent sauver la paix" (Folder 30: 37)
        - "Ceux qui ne se battent pas" (Folder 30: 38)
        - "L'énigme de la paix universelle" (Folder 30: 39)
        - "L'entente franco-turque à Genève" (Folder 30: 40)
        - "L'espoir des nations pacifiques" (Folder 30: 41)
        - "Fusée de guerre ou étoile de paix?" (Folder 30: 42)
        - "Incertitude, inquiétude universelle?" (Folder 30: 43)
        - "Notre Dame des Nations" (Folder 30: 44)
        - "La Pologne définit sa position envers la L. des N." (Folder 30: 45)
        - "Priez pour elle!" (Folder 30: 46)
        - "La Russie et la S.d.N." (Folder 30: 47)
        - "Le soleil se lève" (Folder 30: 48)
        - "La tentation de St. Anthony" (Folder 30: 49)
        - "Vers la paix et la sécurité collective" (Folder 30: 50)
    - Mexico, 1918-1939. (Folder 30: 51)
      Pencil - Dutch language
    - Netherlands, 1918-1939. (Box 31)
      - Domestic politics (Folder 31: 1-66)
      - Domestic politics (Box-folder 32: 1-50)
      - Domestic politics (Box-folder 33: 1-45)
      - Domestic politics (Box-folder 34: 1-41)
      - Domestic politics (Box-folder 35: 1-44)
      - Social and economic conditions. (Box-folder 36: 1-45)
        Images of unemployment, poverty, hunger, and government corruption
      - Social and economic conditions. (Box-folder 37: 1-49)
    - Poland, 1918-1939. (Box 38)
      - Untitled. (Folder 38: 1)
        Ignacy Paderewski at the piano
      - Dutch language (Folder 38: 2-8)
      - French language
        - "Le but" (Folder 38: 9)
        - "Des mamours maintenant" (Folder 38: 10)
        - "Première visite à Varsovie" (Folder 38: 11)
        - "Voyage à Berlin" (Folder 38: 12)
    - Portugal, 1918-1939. (Folder 38: 13)
    - Soviet Union, 1918-1939.
      - Untitled and unidentified (Folder 38: 14)
      - Dutch language (Folder 38: 15-24)
      - English language
        - "Finnish dog. The Russian bear: The nasty beast would not let me go" (Folder 38: 25)
        - "Mephisto to Faust: You can trust me" (Folder 38: 26)
      - French language
        - "La nouvelle constitution bolshéviste: évolution de l'URRS" (Folder 38: 27)
        - "Tolérance: Les clôches rendues aux églises" (Folder 38: 28)
    - Spain, 1918-1939.
      - Dutch language (Folder 38: 29-36)
      - English language
        - "France's dilemma" (Folder 38: 37)
        - "Why notsky!" (Folder 38: 38)
      - French language
        - "Alphonse à la République: Bonne chance et sans rancune!" (Folder 38: 39)
        - "Danse macabre hispano-soviétique" (Folder 38: 40)
        - "La réponse de l'Italie et de l'Allemagne" (Folder 38: 41)
    - United States, 1918-1939. (Box 39)
      - Dutch language (Folder 39: 1-13)
      - English language
        - "Can you hesitate?" (Folder 39: 14)
        - "Eagles" (Folder 39: 15)
        - "Fast asleep" (Folder 39: 16)
        - "Isolationist bloc" (Folder 39: 17)
        - "Sam's getting blue in the face!" (Folder 39: 18)
      - French language
        - "Allons Messieurs! Un bon mouvement!" (Folder 39: 19)
        - "Alors! Pres. Roosevelt.. ." (Folder 39: 20)
        - "L'étoile à Buenos Aires" (Folder 39: 21)
        - "La justice, nous voici!" (Folder 39: 22)
        - "Le mock-out de la Prohibition.. ." (Folder 29: 23)
        - "Le N.I.R.A. va ou n'ira pas" (Folder 29: 24)
        - "Une victoire pour la démocratie.. ." (Folder 29: 25)
      - German language. (Folder 29: 26)
        "Man meint zu schieben und man wird geschoben"
    - World War, 1914-1918 (Box 40)
      - Pencil and charcoal
        - Dutch language (Folder 40: 1)
        - English language
          - "The Crown Prince leaves Pepperhill to occupy a second line of defense prepared beforehand" (Folder 40: 2)
          - "U-Boat haul" (Folder 40: 3)
          - "William: You lead new regiments into the fire, meantime I weep over the terrible losses of the old ones" (Folder 40: 4)
      - Watercolor
        - Dutch language (Folder 40: 5)
        - English language
          - "Kaiser: You are too late" (Folder 40: 6)
          - "Krownprinz: If only I knew what is more dangerous.. ." (Folder 40: 7)
          - "Munitions and armament" (Folder 40: 8)
          - "Off to the sweet country of the windmills" (Folder 40: 9)
          - "We must rescue these beautiful things from destruction or fire" (Folder 40: 10)
  - Sketches of soldiers and battle scenes.
    Includes multiple drawings mounted on single sheets of cardboard
    - Pencil and charcoal. (Folder 40: 11-13)
      Untitled and unidentified
    - Watercolor
      - Untitled and unidentified (Folder 40: 14-27)
      - "American field kitchen" (Folder 40: 28)
      - "German machine gun nest in recent battlefield (sketched on the spot)" (Folder 40: 29)
      - "The non-demobilized: Mine is not the longest watch.. ." (Folder 40: 30)
      - "Preparing for inspection" (Folder 40: 31)
      - "Quiet morning on the front line" (Folder 40: 32)
      - "Suicide Fortress in front of Verdun line, 1918" (Folder 40: 33)
- Large Format Artwork, 1914-1930s. (Box 41)
  Landscape, political cartoons, printed reproductions, and sketches, arranged alphabetically and therein by continent or topic, then title
  - Landscape,"Heather and Pines in Holland," n.d. (Folder 41: 1)
    Pencil Political cartoons. Watercolor
    - World War, 1914-1918 - English language
      - Untitled and unidentified (Folder 41: 2-5)
      - "And he smote the ass.. ." (Folder 41: 6)
      - "Behold the tears of this humanitarian peace-lover" (Folder 41: 7)
      - "Brest-Litovsk" (Folder 41: 8)
      - "The Crown Prince: Will they last out father?" (Folder 41: 9)
      - "A fight to a finish" (Folder 41: 10)
      - "The German mousetrap for Dutch ships" (Folder 41: 11)
      - "The Kaiser to his troops: You will overcome French arrogance and British stubbornness" (Folder 41: 12)
      - "Kaiser to Wilson: You don't mean it!" (Folder 41: 13)
      - "Look'ere Bert, a souvenir of oll' Hindenbeggar's Line" (Folder 41: 14)
      - "Moses-Wilson: I need not destroy them but I might revise them a little" (Folder 41: 15)
      - "U Boat War: Nailed to the mast" (Folder 41: 16)
      - "William and his imperial socialists: If you know how to blindfold them, they will even support their hangman" (Folder 41: 17)
    - Europe, 1930s. (Folder 41: 18-19)
      Pencil - Representations of Adolf Hitler
  - Portrait sketches of soldiers, World War, 1914-1918. (Folder 41: 20-22)
  - Printed reproductions, World War, 1914- 1918 (Folder 41: 23)
  - Sketches of soldiers in battle,and military and civilian life behind the front lines, World War, 1914-1918. (Folder 41: 24-27)
    Watercolor
- Oversize Artwork, 1911-1918. (Box Map case)
  Advertisement, front page for magazine, political cartoons, and sketches, arranged alphabetically
  - Advertisement for Raemaekers' Cartoons With Accompanying Notes By Well-Known English Writers (Map-case 1)
  - Front page, The World Magazine, 1911 (Map-case 2)
  - Political cartoons - World War, 1914-1918
    - "Barbarism - Slavery" (Map-case 3)
    - "Humanity" (Map-case 4)
    - "Judas" (Map-case 5)
    - "Liberty against Kaiserism" (Map-case 6)
    - "Vendredi Saint, 1916 (Map-case 7)
  - Sketches of soldiers in battle, and military and civilian life behind the front lines, World War, 1914-1918 (Map-case 8-12)
- Photocopies of Mattes Removed from Artwork, n.d.. (Box 42)
- Prints, n.d.. (Box 43)
  Limited edition, intaglio process prints
  - Casualties of World War, 1914-1918
    - Civilians (2)
    - French soldiers (2)
  - Cleric with French flag (8)
  - Fishing boats in harbor (2)
  - Nativity (7)
  - Old man (2)
- Artwork by Others, n.d.. (Box 44)
  Drawings and sketches given to Raemaekers in gratitude and recognition of his work. Includes some letters
- Photographs, 1916-1939. (Box Photo file, album shelf)
  24 prints, 10 negatives, 3 postcards, and 1 album of 52 prints, depicting Louis Raemaekers and others
  - 16 prints depicting Louis Raemaekers and others, 1917-1939 (Folder A)
  - 3 postcards depicting cartoons of Louis Raemaekers, n.d. (Folder B)
  - 8 prints depicting Louis Raemaekers and others, n.d. (Folder mC)
  - 10 negatives and 2 prints of cartoons by Louis Raemaekers, n.d. (Folder mD)
  - 1 album of 52 prints depicting Louis Raemaekers and others, 1916-1917 (Box-folder fE)
- Framed Drawing, "When the Rains Came," depiction of Haile Selassie, 1936 (Box Art Rack)